BU Records: Baylor Historical Society, Inclusive: 1883-1982, Bulk: 1883-1981
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
BU Records: Baylor Historical Society
Inclusive: 1883-1982, Bulk: 1883-1981
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
BU/28
Baylor Historical Society
5 document boxes.
BU Records: Baylor Historical Society consist of manuscripts generated by the society and a few people outside the society. The records contain correspondence, financial papers, literary productions, and legal materials.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
The Baylor Historical Society, formed to “stimulate interest in the history of Baylor University,” began in February 1941. Membership was open to anyone interested, and it only cost $1 to join the society.
Though the society was interested in Baylor history in general, members were especially interested in the Texas Collection and Independence, Texas. Since the Texas Collection was the designated repository for Texas history-related items, members directed donations there of original trustee minutes from Baylor’s early history, four dresses from Baylor presidents’ wives, and the collection of William Carey Crane, a former Baylor president. Baylor University started originally in Independence, Texas, and the society was very interested in preserving Baylor’s history there. Members raised money to stabilize the iconic Baylor columns, drew up plans to reconstruct a dorm and operate it as an inn, and lobbied the Texas Legislature to adopt part of Independence as a state park.
Through the 1950s and 1960s, the group raised money to do what they could. Members also helped the Texas State Garden Club landscape around Independence. The society also held regular meetings and luncheons on the Baylor campus, and usually heard a historical paper given at each meeting. The collection contains all known papers read at the yearly meetings.
Though technically not attached to the university in any way, so many employees from Baylor were members of the society that the group enjoyed semi-official status on campus. State luminaries such as Price Daniel and Pat Neff read historical papers to the group, longtime staff members P.D. Browne, Robert L. Reid, Lilly Russell, and E. Bruce Thompson served as officers, and many ancestors of early Baylor-associated families were members.
The Society’s contributions to Baylor and Texas history are many. The time that they operated in Independence is especially significant, since it had been thought Baylor was not active in Independence in the 1940s-1960s. Instead, this society was very active at raising money for the columns at Independence and bringing donations to the Texas Collection.
It is not known when or why the society disbanded. In 1957 the society spent most of their annual meeting taking suggestions from members on how they could improve their organization, indicating that they were not as focused as they had been in the past. Though the society had been formed as a research institution, many members were in favor of reforming the society around other goals. By 1964, the society only had 21 members at their annual meeting, and many of the people who had taken the lead in forming and running the organization had passed away. Longtime member P.D. Browne donated the society’s records to the Texas Collection in 1975, even though some financial papers in the collection have a 1982 date.
Scope and Content
BU Records: Baylor Historical Society begins in 1883 with copies of Baylor Trustee minutes, and goes to 1982 with budget statements. The bulk of the collection is between 1940 and 1960, when the society was most active trying to raise money to restore the Baylor columns in Independence, among other projects. Documents include a large amount of correspondence, legal documents, financial papers, and literary productions. The correspondence series is by far the largest series in the collection.
Arrangement
Prior to current processing, about half of the Baylor Historical Society records were organized very loosely by year, with the rest completely unorganized. Currently, the records are arranged in four series: I. Correspondence, II. Legal Documents, III. Financial Documents, and IV. Literary Productions.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. BU/28. Acquired 1975-07-10
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- History.; Baylor University (Independence, Tex.) -- History.; Baylor University -- Alumni and alumnae.; Baylor University -- Presidents.; Baylor University -- Records and correspondence.
Places
Independence (Tex.).
Subjects
Education, Higher -- Texas -- History; Societies -- Membership -- Texas -- Waco.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Essays.; Financial records.; Financial statements.; Legal documents.; Membership lists.; Speeches.
- Correspondence, 1938-1969, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  - Letters, 1938-1941 February (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1941 March-1942 January 16 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1942 January 19-29 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1942 February-April (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1942 May-1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1944-1945 January 5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1945 January 6-22 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1945 January 23-28 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters, 1945 February 4-15 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters, 1945 February 17-April (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters, 1945 June-November (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters, 1946 January 7-17 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters, 1946 January 22-27 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters, 1946 February 4-7 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters, 1946 February 8-March (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters, 1946 June-September 23 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letters, 1946 September 24-December (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letters, 1947 January (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letters, 1947 February-May (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letters, 1947 September-October 13 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letters, 1947 October 21-31 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letters, 1947 November 1-22 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letters, 1947 November 25-December 20 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Letters, 1948 January 9-16 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Letters, 1948 January 17-23 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Letters, 1948 January 24-28 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Letters, 1948 January 29-February 16 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Letters, 1948 February 19-April (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Letters, 1948 May 1-19 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Letters, 1948 May 21-26 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Letters, 1948 June-July (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Letters, 1948 August (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Letters, 1948 September (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1949 January 11-24 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1949 January 12-28 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1949 January 29-February 14 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1949 February 15-March (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1949 May (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1949 June-December (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1950 February-June (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Letters, 1950 July-December (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letters, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Letters, 1952 April-May 7 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Letters, 1952 May 8 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Letters, 1952 May 9 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Letters, 1952 May 17-June (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Letters, 1952 July-October (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Letters, 1953 January-June 2 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Letters, 1953 June 12-30 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Letters, 1953 July (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Letters, 1954 January-June (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Letters, 1954 July-November (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Letters, 1955 January-February (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Letters, 1955 April-May 12 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Letters, 1955 May 13-20 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Letters, 1955 May 24-June 8 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Letters, 1955 June 10-November 8 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Letters, 1955 November 16-1956 June 20 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Letters, 1956 June 30-November (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Letters, 1957 January-May 19 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Letters, 1957 May 20-31 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Letters, 1957 June-1958 March (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Letters, 1958 April (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Letters, 1958 October-1959 March 20 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Letters, 1959 March 21-April (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Letters, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Letters, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Letters, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Letters, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Legal Documents, 1947, undated; 2
  - General, 1947, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Articles of Incorporation, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Financial Documents, 1941-1982, undated; 3
  - Financial: General, 1942-1969 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - General, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Luncheons, 1946-1953 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Reports, 1941-1949 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Reports, 1950-1962 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Reports, 1963-1972 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Dues, 1941-1945 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Dues, 1946-1955 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Dues, 1956-1967 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Dues, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements, 1942-1948 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements, 1950-1954 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements, 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements, 1962-1966 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements, 1969 June (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements, 1969 July-1980, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Budget Statements, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Budget Statements, 1966-1972 May (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Budget Statements, 1972 June-October (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Budget Statements, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Budget Statements, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Literary Productions, 1883-1971; 4
  - General, 1938-1946 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - General, 1948-1955 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - General (1 of 2), undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - General (2 of 2), undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Reports, 1946-1956 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Reports, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Research, 1883-1888 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Research, 1890 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Programs, 1945-1955 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Programs, 1961-1969 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Memorial Tributes, 1954-1963, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Membership Lists (1 of 2), 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Membership Lists (2 of 2), 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Membership Lists, 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Membership Lists (1 of 3), 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Membership Lists (2 of 3), 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Membership Lists (3 of 3), 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Membership Lists, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Membership Lists, 1950-1953 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Membership Lists, 1954-1956 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Membership Lists, 1958-1965 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Membership Lists, 1966-1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Membership Mailing Lists (1 of 3), 1956 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Membership Mailing Lists (2 of 3), 1956 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Membership Mailing Lists (3 of 3), 1956 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Membership Mailing Lists, Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1942-1949 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1950-1957 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1961-1963 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, 1964-1968, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Society Record Forms, 1940-1952 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Society Record Forms, 1953-1962, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Luncheon Reservations, 1946-1949 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Luncheon Reservations, 1953-1963, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Luncheon Reservations, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Essays: General (1 of 3), undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Essays: General (2 of 3), undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Essays: General (3 of 3), undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Essays: Carroll Essay, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Speeches, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Speeches: Price Daniel, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Speeches: Price Daniel: Notes, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Speeches: Joseph M. Dawson, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Speeches: Herbert Gambrell (1 of 2), 1947 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Speeches: Herbert Gambrell (2 of 2), 1947 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Speeches: Guy Nelson Jr. (1 of 2), 1961 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Speeches: Guy Nelson Jr. (2 of 2), 1961 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Minutes, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Minutes, 1945-1946 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Minutes, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Minutes, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Minutes, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Minutes, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Minutes, 1951-1953 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Minutes, 1954-1957 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Minutes, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Minutes, 1961-1963 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Minutes, 1964-1971 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Membership Cards: Single-Sided (1 of 3), 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Membership Cards: Single-Sided (2 of 3), 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Membership Cards: Single-Sided (3 of 3), 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Membership Cards: Double-Sided (1 of 2), 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Membership Cards: Double-Sided (2 of 2), 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Research Cards (1 of 2), undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Research Cards (2 of 2), undated (Box 5, Folder 4)